Go!
Go! We pick up today at the very bottom of כ"ז ע"א.
Chaf-Zayin Amud Aleph. We'll
and just yesterday we had obviously a tremendous focus on the discussion
of עבודה וקורבנות Avodah veKorbanot which is an ongoing theme. David asks
about the fact that the שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei opens with עבודה.
Avodah. So is that an emphasis of the עבודה? Avodah? And I
would say actually to be in all honesty I haven't thought about
that but I think it's an excellent point. What I had noticed
in also in terms of the שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei and with
all of our talking about how everybody assumes it's all about קורבנות
Korbanot is two things in particular, thank you. For one I've already
mentioned which is even before the עבודה Avodah what we've added, I
mean was added later but ה' שפתי תפתח ופי יגיד תהלתך. Hashem
sefatai tiftach ufi yagid tehilatecha. In the context where that appears in
תהלים, Tehillim, the פסוק Pasuk that comes right afterwards is כי לא
תחפוץ עולה וזבח, Ki lo tachpotz olah va'zevach, that you do not
desire sacrifices, you want our hearts, you want our words. So it's
really an exact contrast to תפילה Tefillah as more desired by God
than the sacrifices.
And that's number one. Number two, the one ברכה Bracha that we
have that is that is really about the עבודה, Avodah, רצה ה'
אלוהינו, Retzei Hashem Elokeinu, right? בעמך ישראל ובתפילתם, be'amcha Yisrael ubitfilatam, right?
So it's there's you don't
you never mention sacrifices explicitly. That's supposed to be the עבודה Avodah
כביכול, kiveyachol, I know, but you say ובתפילתם, ubitfilatam, והשב העבודה, vahashev
ha'avodah, ואישי ישראל. ve'ishei Yisrael.
Where else do we refer to sacrifices as אישי ישראל? Ishei Yisrael?
It has got to be the most abstract way, indirect way of
referring to sacrifices. So I think it's quite fascinating how much sacrifices
are not in the שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei even where they should
be in regarding this issue about is it כנגד קורבנות keneged korbanot
or not כנגד קורבנות? keneged korbanot? And I will say in general
it seems to me, I wrote an article about this, that there
are some תנאים Tannaim that think that קורבנות Korbanot are the ideal
and that תפילה Tefillah is some substitute, and there are other תנאים
Tannaim that feel very strongly that תפילות Tefillot are more desired by
God than קורבנות. Korbanot. And there were like these types of discussions
post חורבן הבית Churban HaBayit about these issues. So I think that
and the idea that it opens with עבודה Avodah is particularly significant.
Do you want to add? It's just it's just the interesting nuance
for me is that it does seem like the פשט Pshat in
the תנ"ך Tanach is that when the classic prophetic criticism of Israel
about sacrifices, the criticism as I understood it is not we would
rather I'd rather have your prayer in lieu of sacrifice, but rather
I don't want empty sacrifice. Exactly, meaning empty ritual. Meaning I want
the structure of the sacrifice as a vessel for conveying your heart.
Right, absolutely.
Or
not only also consistent with ethical behavior and otherwise proper behavior. Correct.
Sacrifices mean nothing if it's not reflected in all in all other
aspects
in the full human being. Exactly. That still allows you to say
verbal articulation could substitute for that, but your דאוונען davening means nothing
if when you get out onto the street the way you behave
is not reflective of what you were doing.
Right, I think I think the possibility that תפילות Tefillot are a
bit more important than sacrifices comes up after the חורבן, Churban, but
I do think it's important to note that the phenomenon of תפילה,
Tefillah, not just in אברהם יצחק ויעקב Avraham Yitzchak veYaakov throughout תנ"ך,
Tanach, דוד המלך David HaMelech wrote
תהילים, Tehillim, and according to many scholars תהילים Tehillim was basically the
first prayer book and something that maybe they said together with sacrifices
or those that were not in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So
the human sort of experience and need for
תפילה, Tefillah, I don't I'm not even sure that they were always
on the same plane. I mean I'm not even sure that even
when there was a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash it was like one
way we connect to God is קורבנות, Korbanot, one way is תפילה.
Tefillah. It could be that they were seen as qualitatively different. The
way you do כפרה, Kappara, the way you do certain types of
עבודה Avodah is קורבנות, Korbanot, and the way you do
personal prayer is תפילה, Tefillah, saying תהילים, Tehillim, it could be that
they were never sort of seen as one or the other but
sort of doing different types of
functions. Okay, let's go. We do have to start.
רמב"ם Rambam seems to think קורבנות Korbanot are kind of...
yeah that clearly רמב"ם Rambam is in מורה נבוכים Moreh Nevuchim thinks
that קורבנות Korbanot is just a compromise to human nature and not
the ideal. But also if you look at the רמב"ם Rambam even
thinks תפילה Tefillah is not the ideal but that's for another time.
The only point I was going to mention is that since we're
not since the תפילה כנגד קורבנות Tefillah keneged korbanot you started the
debate on, certainly מוספים Musafim aren't in there, which is why which
is why the practice is then to put the קורבן Korban in
מוסף, Musaf, right?
You wouldn't you wouldn't do that in שחרית. Shacharit. Well no that
is true, everybody so we'll end with that point for now. Everybody
agrees as we said yesterday that מוסף Musaf is כנגד קורבן. keneged
korban. The גמרא Gemara essentially makes that point and מוסף Musaf is
the one place where we explicitly mention the קורבן. Korban. Correct. Okay,
so now we continue here. The very bottom of כ"ז ע"א. Chaf-Zayin
Amud Aleph. The גמרא Gemara says רבי ירמיה היכי עביד הכי, Rabbi
Yirmeyah heichi avid hachi, last line, how did רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeyah
do this? דאוונען Daven behind his רבי? Rebbi? והאמר...
I think that was what רבי ירמיה did. Yes, he דאוונד davened
behind רב, Rav, והאמר רב יהודה אמר רב. v'ha'amar Rav Yehudah amar
Rav. So רב יהודה Rav Yehudah says in the name of רב,
Rav, so the same one he דאוונד davened behind, רב. Rav. it's
taught, you know, there's a tradition from רב Rav *Rav* that says
לעולם אל יתפלל אדם לא כנגד רבו ולא אחורי רבו *L'olam al
yitpalel adam lo k'neged rabbo v'lo achorei rabbo*. A person should never
דאוון davven *daven* like side-by-side with his רבי *rebbi*, it seems like
he's saying he's equal or behind his רבי *rebbi*, either because it's
somewhat disrespectful looking at the back of your רבי *rebbi* or because
it looks like you're bowing down to your רבי *rebbi*. So the
very רבי *rebbi* he דאוונד davvened. *davened* behind, רב Rav *Rav*, was
the one who said you shouldn't be דאוונינג davvening *davening* behind him.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ותניא *v'tanya*, רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*
אומר *omer*, המתפלל *hamitpalel* אחורי *achorei* רבו *rabbo*, somebody דאוונס *davens* behind
his רבי *rebbi*. והנותן *V'hanoten* שלום *shalom* לרבו *l'rabbo* והמחזיר *v'hamachzir* שלום
*shalom* לרבו *l'rabbo*, and if somebody says שלום עליכם *Shalom Aleichem* to
his רבי *rebbi* or responds to his רבי *rebbi*, we'll talk about
that in a minute. והחולק *V'hacholek* על *al* ישיבתו *yeshivato* של *shel*
רבו *rabbo*, and somebody that disagrees with the positions, the ישיבה yeshiva.
*yeshiva* here, but presumably like the positions, the הלכה halacha *halakhic* positions
of his רבי *rebbi*. והאומר *V'haomer* דבר *davar* שלא *shelo* שמע *shama*
מפי *mipi* רבו *rabbo*, and somebody who says something he didn't hear
directly from his רבי *rebbi*, גורם *gorem* לשכינה *lishchina* שתסתלק *shetistalek* מישראל
*miyisrael*, causes the שכינה *Shechina* to depart from ישראל Israel, *Israel*. So
how could he have דאוונד davvened *davened* behind his רבי *rebbi*? So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says שאני *shani* רבי ירמיה בר אבא *Rabbi
Yirmiya bar Abba*, he was different. דתלמיד חבר הוה *d'talmid chaver hava*,
he was a, he was a student slash colleague. He was like
a younger colleague. So yes, he revered his רבי *rebbi* but he
was also his colleague and therefore it was acceptable. Okay, maybe it
would have been if he דאוונד davvened *davened* side-by-side, maybe that would
have been appropriate but that was acceptable. והיינו דקאמר ליה *V'hainu d'ka'amar
leh* רבי ירמיה בר אבא *Rabbi Yirmiya bar Abba* לרב *l'Rav*. So
therefore, okay, so wait first second. So let me just say one
thing about what we just read. So נותן שלום לרבו *noten shalom
l'rabbo*, what's the matter with saying שלום עליכם *Shalom Aleichem*? So רש"י
*Rashi* says and תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafot* says it means that you say
שלום עליכם *Shalom Aleichem* and you don't say שלום עליכם רבי ומורי
*Shalom Aleichem Rabbi u'Mori*.
It's possible to have assumed otherwise that sometimes there should be such
a class difference that you're not in a position to say שלום
עליכם *Shalom Aleichem* to me. I can say שלום עליכם *Shalom Aleichem*
to you, you can't say שלום עליכם *Shalom Aleichem* to me. המהרש"א
*The Maharsha* points out that we actually find that in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* about an עבד *eved* and a רב *rav*, a slave
is not supposed to say שלום עליכם *Shalom Aleichem* to the רב
*rav* master, you know because of the subservience or the lower class
difference. But he says cause רש"י *Rashi* and תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* did
not want to say that here because they thought that was maybe
something specific in terms of that huge gap between slave and a
free person, not maybe appropriate here. So they interpreted it that the
problem was that you did not say it with the honorific. You
just said it like he was a pal. Hey, how you doing?
Okay, you didn't, you know you didn't do it with the right
type of honor. Now one other point though and we'll get about
this about רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* is he says and somebody who
says something he didn't hear from his רבי *rebbi*. So as המהרש"א
*the Maharsha* correctly points out, what are you talking about? All through
ש"ס *Shas* people are being creative and saying things they didn't hear
from their רבי *rebbi*. And my point is you know what, you're
right. But that is, המהרש"א *the Maharsha* has his answer but the,
but the you know the best answer is that רבי אליעזר *Rabbi
Eliezer* says elsewhere that he took pride that he never said anything
he didn't hear from his רבי *rebbi* and from other stories about
רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* תנא Tanna, שמותי *Tanna Shammuti*, other types of
things it's very clear that רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer's* approach to תורה
שבעל פה Torah sheba'al peh, *Torah she'ba'al peh* was pure transmission. Was
what you learned from your רבי *rebbi* and you pass it down.
What did your רבי *rebbi* learn it from? He learned it from
his רבי *rebbi*. What'd he learn it from? They go all the
way back to משה *Moshe*. But תורה Torah. שבעל פה *Torah she'ba'al
peh* is transmission. It's not about creativity, it's not about coming up
with new ideas. So that's a particular רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* tradition
which is sort of strongly opposed by רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva *Rabbi
Akiva* who is who is so so who is one of his
תלמידים Talmidim *talmidim* and דורש תגים *doresh tagim*. So רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva* was חולק *cholek* on his רבי *rebbi* in this very issue
about not being חולק *cholek* on your רבי *rebbi* and not saying
things that you didn't learn from your רבי *rebbi*. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. והיינו דקאמר ליה *V'hainu d'ka'amar leh* רבי ירמיה
בר אבא *Rabbi Yirmiya bar Abba* לרב *l'Rav*. So to prove that
he was a younger colleague is that רבי ירמיה בר אבא *Rabbi
Yirmiya bar Abba* asked רב *Rav* מי *mi* בדלת *badalta*? Have you,
have you, have you made הבדלה Havdalah *havdalah* like have you, have
you separated from doing מלאכה melacha? *melakha* when he דאוונד davvened, *davened*
early? So and what's the proof? אמר ליה amar leh,
*Amar leh* he said והיינו דקאמר ליה רבי ירמיה בר אבא אמר
ליה amar leh, *v'hainu d'ka'amar leh Rabbi Yirmiya bar Abba amar leh*
אין *in*, בדילנא *badilna*. Yes, I דאוונד davvened *davened* מעריב Maariv *Maariv*
early and I stopped doing מלאכה melacha. *melakha*. ולא אמר Amar, *V'lo
amar* מי *mi* בדיל *badil* מר *mar*? Has the master stopped? Meaning
referring to him in third person. He referred to him in second
person. So it shows that he is of a colleague nature because
if you're student nature you refer in the third person. So now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* moving beyond that and going back to the
theme that if you, you can דאוון davven *daven* שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*
early, מעריב Maariv *Maariv* early, and here we're introducing the idea you
stop doing מלאכה melacha. *melakha* when you דאוון davven *daven* it early.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ומי *U'mi* בדיל *badil*? Is it
really true that you separate from מלאכה melacha *melakha* you don't do
מלאכה melacha, *melakha* if you דאוון davven *daven* מעריב Maariv *Maariv* early?
והאמר *V'ha'amar* רב אבינא *Rav Avina*, didn't רב אבינא *Rav Avina* say
פעם אחת *pa'am achat* התפלל *hitpalel* רבי *Rebbi* של *shel* שבת Shabbos.
*Shabbat* בערב שבת Shabbos *b'erev Shabbat*? One time רבי *Rebbi* דאוונד davvened
*davened* שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* when it was still Friday, מעריב Maariv *Maariv*.
ונכנס *V'nichnas* למרחץ *l'merchatz*, and afterwards he went into the bathhouse. ויצא
*V'yatza* וביקש *v'bikeish* ושנה *v'shana* לנו *lanu* פרקין *pirkin*, and he taught
us our chapter. ועדיין *v'adayin* לא *lo* חשכה *chashicha*, and it wasn't
yet evening, it wasn't yet dark. So he did all that, he
took care of all that stuff before שבת Shabbos? *Shabbos*. Proof is
he went into a bathhouse, you see he didn't consider it to
be שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*. So אמר Amar, *Amar* רבא *Rava*, ההוא *hahu*
דנכנס *d'nichnas* להזיע *l'hazia*. When he went into the bathhouse you're not
allowed to rabbinically even if the water is heated up before שבת
Shabbos. *Shabbos*, clearly that was the case here it was before שבת
Shabbos, *Shabbos*, you are still not allowed to fully immerse into hot
water because of a concern that even if the water was preheated
you would come to heat it up if you, once you start
doing that on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat*. So that's why you can't go
into a heated bathhouse on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*. And at a second
level
Obviously they're logically connected, but it was a second stage of the
תקנה. So the גמרא Gemara. says he just went in for the
steam
room, לפרשויץ, le-pershvitz, וקודם גזירה אחת היא, ve-kodem gezeirah achat hi, and
it was before they made the second level of the גזירה gezeirah
to prohibit that. So really he did start, you know, treating it
as שבת, Shabbos. but this was at a time when this was
allowed even on שבת. Shabbos.
So do I understand the הוה אמינא hava amina here is you
can דאוון davven an מעריב Maariv of שבת Shabbos. and then do
מלאכה? melacha.
Yes, that is the הוה אמינא. hava amina. Okay, and I will
say something when we conclude about the רמב"ם's Rambam position. And that
is what the גמרא Gemara is trying to figure out. So with
one statement we made that we allowed you to דאוון davven early.
That just means that we פסקן pasken to strike like ר' יהודה,
Rebbi Yehuda, you know, we also allow you on מוצאי שבת Motzaei
Shabbos to דאוון davven מעריב Maariv. of חול chol early, ironically, bizarrely,
even though you're not allowed to do מלאכה. melacha So maybe you
can דאוון davven שבת Shabbos, early even though you haven't made it
into שבת? Shabbos Right.
But it's not like you can light שבת Shabbos. candles and still
do מלאכה. melacha. So it's similar, it sounds similar. Exactly. Okay.
Yep. So the גמרא Gemara says, איני והא אביי שרא ליה לרב
דימי בר ליוואי Aini ve-ha Abaye shara leh le-Rav Dimi bar Livai
לחברויי סאלי le-chavroye salei to sort of like blacken or whatever he
did some type of a thing with these baskets. He smoked them.
I don't even understand exactly what it was, but anyway, he did
some type of thing involving fire and these baskets and manufacturing them.
So the גמרא Gemara says, and that was after he had דאוונד.
davvened, טעותא הואי. ta'uta havai. No, that was a mistake. He דאוונד
davvened מעריב Maariv, thinking it was night. You know, as you point
out before they didn't have clocks, it was a dark cloudy day,
thinking it was sunset. Then the clouds separated, he realized it was
still day. So there it didn't count. It didn't count that they
were implicitly מקבל שבת mekabbel Shabbos by דאוונינג davvening because it was
a mistake. They didn't intend to be מקבל שבת mekabbel Shabbos early.
They דאוונד because they thought it was already שבת. Shabbos So the
גמרא Gemara says, וטעותא מי הדר, ve-ta'uta mi hadar, who says you
can take back a mistake? Even if it was a mistake, maybe
you should be stuck. והאמר רב אבידן, ve-ha-amar Rav Avidan, says רב
אבידן, Rav Avidan, פעם אחת נתקשרו שמים בעבים, pa'am achat nitkashru shamayim
be-avim, one day the clouds like the sky was darkened with clouds,
כסבורים העם לומר חשיכה הוא, kesvurim ha-am lomar chasheicha hu, everybody thought
it was already dark, it was שבת, Shabbos ונכנסו לבית הכנסת והתפללו,
ve-nichnasu le-veit ha-keneset ve-hitpalelu, they went into the שול shul and they
דאוונד, של מוצאי שבת בשבת, shel Motzaei Shabbos be-Shabbos, they דאוונד the
Saturday night דאוונינג davvening on שבת. Shabbos ונתפזרו העבים, ve-nitpazru ha-avim, and
then the clouds separated, וזרחה החמה, ve-zarchah ha-chamah, the sun shone. So
obviously they're not allowed to do מלאכה melacha until שבת Shabbos is
over. So the question here is not מלאכה, melacha. the question here
is are they יצא תפילה? yotzei tefillah? Okay, so they דאוונד the
מעריב Maariv early thinking it was Saturday night, and they found out
it wasn't. ובאו ושאלו את רבי, u-bau ve-sha'alu et Rebbi, and they
asked ר', Rebbi, ואמר הואיל והתפללו התפללו. ve-amar ho'il ve-hitpalelu hitpalelu. Okay,
they דאוונד, they were יצא. yotzei. Now it's funny, we never were
asking whether you were יצא תפילה, yotzei tefillah, we were asking whether
it was considered a קבלה. kabbalah. Whether when you דאוון davven thinking
it's the wrong time, whether it counted as an early acceptance of
שבת. Shabbos The גמרא Gemara somehow thinks that it's similar, that if,
here seems to be the mindset of the גמרא. Gemara If you're
knowing that you're דאוונינג davvening. early, you want to דאוון early, it's
one thing. Then you are defining somehow that although it's early, this
is the nighttime דאוונינג. davvening But if you think you're דאוונינג davvening.
and it's already night, then maybe it only counts if it's genuinely
night, because you're not intending for it to be an early דאוונינג.
davvening. Maybe you have to label it an early דאוונינג. davvening, So
in this case, they thought it was night, they didn't, it turns
out, maybe it shouldn't count. You see that it does count though.
If that can count even though they didn't label it an early
דאוונינג, davvening, so maybe it should count on Friday, on Friday afternoon
even though they didn't label it. But even so, even with that
הוה אמינא, hava amina, it's so what? So let it count as
a דאוונינג, davvening. but let it not be a קבלה kabbalah of
שבת. Shabbos And the גמרא Gemara so it's a very strange גמרא
Gemara why it is assuming that just because it counts the מעריב
Maariv of מוצאי שבת, Motzaei Shabbos, it means that when you דאוון
ערב שבת Erev Shabbos by mistake, it counts as a קבלה. kabbalah.
And the גמרא Gemara does not reject that in the answer. The
גמרא Gemara says, שאני ציבור דלא מטרחינן להו. shani tzibbur d'lo matrachi'nan
lehu. Yeah, by the ציבור, tzibbur, if the whole מניין minyan דאוונד
early, then we're not, even if by mistake, we're not going to
make them go back. So they outside, they see it's still שבת.
Shabbos Right. So they have to desist from doing מלאכה. melacha. Right,
but when it's really מוצאי שבת, Motzaei Shabbos, they don't have to
go back and דאוון מעריב. Maariv Correct. Correct. And that actually is
the הלכה halacha even if you, even if, no, no. So listen,
but even intentionally you can, we're going to find out in a
minute. Not only that, you can say, you can make הבדלה Havdalah,
without lighting a candle once it's פלג המנחה. Plag HaMincha. Once it's
towards the end of שבת, Shabbos you can דאוון מעריב, Maariv you
can make הבדלה, havdalah you obviously can't do מלאכה melacha, until שבת
Shabbos. is absolutely over. And that is true even if you do
it intentionally. The only issue here is if you made a mistake
thinking it was already sunset, does it still count or not? Because
there you weren't intending for it to be early, you intended for
it to be at the time and it wound up being early.
And here the גמרא Gemara makes a distinction: for the ציבור tzibbur
a mistake it will still count, and for a יחיד yachid it
has to be only intentional. But it still doesn't get to the
point about the, about the, it's one thing to say it counts
as דאוונינג. davvening The גמרא's Gemara assumption that if it's going to
count as דאוונינג ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, it's also going to necessarily
be a קבלת שבת. Kabbalas Shabbos. And I want to say something
about this. So this גמרא Gemara on דף כ"ז עמוד א'. daf
chof-zayin amud aleph. Here if you דאווען daven early on ערב שבת
erev Shabbos it implies a קבלת שבת kabbalat Shabbos and although the
גמרא Gemara questions it, it tries to get around it. If you
look this assumes the idea that there is a concept of being
מקבל שבת mekabel Shabbos early, תוספת שבת. tosefet Shabbos. Now there's a
גמרא Gemara in a number of places that talks about a מצוה
mitzvah of תוספת יום הכפורים tosefet Yom HaKippurim which we learned from
a פסוק pasuk of accepting יום כיפור Yom Kippur early and then
it extends it to שבת. Shabbos According to some ראשונים rishonim that
the extension to שבת Shabbos is only דרבנן derabanan but even if
it's only דרבנן derabanan fine there's an idea of דרבנןly derabanan accepting
שבת Shabbos early and that's how everybody reads this גמרא Gemara and
you need that idea of accepting שבת Shabbos early in order to
allow you to דאווען מעריב daven Maariv early or the flip when
you דאווען מעריב daven Maariv early it's an implicit קבלת שבת. kabbalat
Shabbos. רמב״ם Rambam interestingly never mentions the concept of קבלת שבת kabbalat
Shabbos early. I mean not just the תפילה קבלת שבת. tefillah kabbalat
Shabbos. He mentions תוספת שבת tosefet Shabbos for יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
תוספת יום הכפורים tosefet Yom HaKippurim to start יום כיפור Yom Kippur
early when you start it and end it but he never mentions
the idea that if early שבת Shabbos you say I'm דאווען davening
or I'm מקבל שבת mekabel Shabbos on myself that all of a
sudden it becomes שבת Shabbos and I can't do מלאכה. melacha You
won't find that in the רמב״ם. Rambam. And when the רמב״ם Rambam
deals with why can you דאווען מעריב daven Maariv early and also
sort of like why can you rely on רב יהודה Reb Yehuda
and דאווען מעריב daven Maariv פלג המנחה plag hamincha he says yeah
because מעריב Maariv is only רשות reshus so therefore you can דאווען
מעריב daven Maariv a little before the time. And he doesn't make
a big deal about the idea of this being connected to קבלת
שבת kabbalat Shabbos and let's face it in the flip case you
can דאווען חול daven chol Saturday late afternoon even though it's not
חול chol so why not דאווען שבת daven Shabbos Friday late afternoon
without the concept of קבלת שבת? kabbalat Shabbos? And one other point
about that so what about the fact of oh but make קידוש?
Kiddush? Everybody agrees you make קידוש Kiddush if you start שבת Shabbos
early. So if you look at the רמב״ם Rambam when he speaks
about the מצוה mitzvah of making קידוש Kiddush he says by קידוש
והבדלה Kiddush vehavdalah the idea to designate שבת Shabbos at its beginning
and at its end or a little before a little after. We
don't make הבדלה havdalah. like exactly at the moment of the end
you know so the idea to designate שבת Shabbos you designate it
a little before the beginning of שבת. Shabbos So for the רמב״ם
Rambam both the idea of קידוש Kiddush on ערב שבת erev Shabbos
if you make an early שבת Shabbos and דאווענינג davening is he
has that concept even without the concept of תוספת שבת tosefet Shabbos
of the idea that somehow you've brought שבת Shabbos in early. Is
it שבת Shabbos when we make קידוש? Kiddush? No it is not.
You have done the מצוה mitzvah of קידוש Kiddush you have designated
that שבת Shabbos is about to arrive but שבת Shabbos only begins
at sunset. I know it's very bizarre to get your head around
but I guess he sort of means in other words a question
for me is so what does it mean when you're saying the
words of those prayers for מעריב on שבת Shabbos when we say
מקדש השבת? mekadesh hashabbos? Right so in other words your explanation in
this context is I am saying the words of this prayer to
acknowledge my awareness that when it gets dark שבת Shabbos. will come?
Right looking forward to the שבת Shabbos. that is about to come.
I can say that דאווענינג davening according to this I'm not saying
this is the נורמה. norma. And make קידוש Kiddush and then I
can turn on the air conditioner or do whatever I need to
do last minute? Right theoretically. Right. The גמרא Gemara here seems to
be totally rejecting that but if you read the רמב״ם Rambam closely
the רמב״ם Rambam does not speak about not doing מלאכה melacha, after
דאווענינג מעריב. davening Maariv. He does not speak about תוספת שבת. tosefet
Shabbos. He just says yeah you can דאווען daven a little early.
Now you are correct saying the ברכה מקדש השבת beracha mekadesh hashabbos
when it's חול chol is different than saying a weekday תפילה tefillah
on שבת Shabbos because you're just you're not saying anything about it
not being שבת Shabbos but we're about to see you're going to
say הבדלה. havdalah. You're going to say הבדלה בחונן הדעת havdalah bechonen
hadaas so it's the same type of a problem and it doesn't
yeah and you can say it in anticipation without it actually being
the beginning yes. But here isn't the point of this that you're
דאווענינג davening not for the bringing in שבת Shabbos but for the
מעריב from שבת Shabbos to חול? chol? So you're allowed to do
it earlier and then we accept that you did it earlier. Yes
you count for מעריב and הבדלה. havdalah. It doesn't count to let
you do מלאכה. melacha, You have to wait for שבת Shabbos to
be over in order to do מלאכה. He doesn't have to דאווען
מעריב daven Maariv and you don't have to make הבדלה. havdalah Right.
And a way that this can happen now we're getting a little
ahead of ourselves but let's just read a little bit more because
we'll see the הבדלה havdalah case and then I'll take your question.
אמר רב חייא בר אבין Amar Rav Chiya bar Avin רב צלי
של שבת בערב שבת. Rav tzalay shel Shabbos be'erev Shabbos. So רב
דאווענד שבת davened Shabbos on when it was still Friday ורבי יאשיה
מצלי של מוצאי שבת בשבת. veRebbi Yoshiya matzlay shel motzaei Shabbos beShabbos.
And now we're doing the flip case.
רב יאשיה Reb Yoshiya
דאווענד davened the מוצאי שבת תפילה motzaei Shabbos tefillah at Saturday late
afternoon שבת Shabbos afternoon. רב צלי של שבת בערב שבת. Rav tzalay
shel Shabbos be'erev Shabbos. Now when רב דאווענד שבת davened Shabbos on
ערב שבת erev Shabbos here's exactly the issue we were just discussing
אומר קידושא על הכוס או אינו אומר קידושא על הכוס? omer kiddusha
al hakos o eino omer kiddusha al hakos? Now that you've דאווענד
davened made דאווענד שבת davened Shabbos early can you go home and
make and you know and do קידוש Kiddush or not? אומר קידושא
על הכוס. omer kiddusha al hakos. Do you do קידוש Kiddush or
not? You know it's not real שבת Shabbos, yet you just דאווענד
davened early. So the גמרא Gemara says תא שמע דאמר רב נחמן
אמר שמואל מתפלל אדם של שבת בערב שבת ואומר קידושא על הכוס.
ta shema de'amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel mitpalel adam shel Shabbos be'erev
Shabbos ve'omer kiddusha al hakos. You can say קידוש Kiddush if you
made שבת Shabbos if you דאווענד davened an early שבת. Shabbos והלכתא
כוותיה. vehilchata kavatei. That's how we rule. רבי יאשיה מצלי של מוצאי
שבת בשבת. Rebbi Yoshiya matzlay shel motzaei Shabbos beShabbos. רב יאשיה Reb
Yoshiya דאווענד מוצאי שבת davened motzaei Shabbos when it's still שבת. Now
the question is אומר הבדלה על הכוס או אינו אומר הבדלה על
הכוס? omer havdalah al hakos o eino omer havdalah al hakos? Do
you say הבדלה havdala on a כוס kos or not and it's
assuming that you it almost takes for granted that you're saying the
הבדלה havdala in the שמנה עשרה. Shmonei Esrei. If you say you're
דאווענינג davening מוצאי שבת, Motzei Shabbos, that means with the הבדלה havdala
in the שמנה עשרה. Shmonei Esrei. So now, could you even go
so far as to make הבדלה על הכוס? havdala al hakos? So
because obviously that's different, right? It's one thing to say we פסקן
pasken like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and we let you דאווען מעריב.
daven Maariv. And once you דאווען מעריב, daven Maariv, so מעריב מוצאי,
Maariv Motzoei, you know, this מעריב gets a הבדלה havdala in it.
To actually do the ritual of הבדלה havdala, is really like, you
know, saying it without the אש. eish. Yeah, you would say you're
holding by a pre-existing... All right, but it doesn't matter. Yes, possible,
but let's bracket the אש. eish. But you know, that really sounds
like something you really wanted to be real מוצאי שבת. Motzei Shabbos.
So the גמרא Gemara says, תא שמע, ta shma, דאמר רב יהודה
משמיה דשמואל, d'amar Rav Yehuda mishmei d'Shmuel, מטועי של מוצאי שבת, m'toei
shel Motzei Shabbos, ואומר הבדלה על הכוס. v'omer havdala al hakos. And
that's the way we rule. And if you take a
look like תוספות, Tosafot it says, where is...?
מטועי של מוצאי שבת,
m'toei shel
Motzei Shabbos, when you're דאווענינג davening מוצאי שבת Motzei Shabbos early, תוספות
Tosafot, says, יש לומר דהכא מיירי שיש לו צורך מצווה לעשות במוצאי
שבת,
yesh
lomar
d'hacha mairi sheyesh lo tzorech mitzvah la'asos b'Motzei Shabbos, כגון ללכת למול
תינוק,
k'gon lalechet
limol
tinok, דלא יהא לו יין להבדלה אם לא יקדים,
d'lo yehei
lo yayin
l'havdala im lo yakdim, דודאי צריך להוסיף מן החול על הקודש דאורייתא.
d'vadai tzarich l'hosif min hachol al hakodesh d'Oraisa. He wants to know
why can you דאווען daven early? You're supposed to say we're supposed
to add to שבת before, you're supposed to add to שבת after.
So by making הבדלה, havdala although you can't do מלאכה, but as
soon as שבת is over, it's over, and we're supposed to add
a few minutes after שבת is over. Oh, he means he has
to travel to do a ברית bris next morning. אבל בחינם לא,
Aval b'chinam lo, not בחינם. b'chinam. ופשיטא דלא מצי למעבד מלאכה עד
חשיכה, U'pshita d'lo matzi l'ma'avad melacha ad chasheicha, right? Obviously there's no
benefit of doing it early, you know, in terms of because מלאכה
you have to wait. So תוספות Tosafot adds the idea that it
has to be some type of a צורך מצווה tzorech mitzvah or
some type of a דוחק. dochak. But that is the way we
rule and this will happen. Let's say you're somewhere and your plane
is departing, you know, ממש mamash an hour after צאת, Tzeis, after
צאת, Tzeis, and you're anxious, you gotta be ready or whatever, so
you דאווען daven early, you make הבדלה havdala, early so you can
jump in a cab like first thing as soon as it becomes
צאת. Tzeis. You know, so there are times where you rely on
this, but obviously... What? You can דאווען daven it anyway, even if
it's not... בשעת צורך, B'shas tzorech, בשעת הדחק b'shas hadechak and so
on, if you need to do a מצווה. mitzvah. Yes. Practical example:
Northern Europe in the summer, שבת ends very late. You דאווען, daven,
make הבדלה, havdala don't do מלאכה, go to bed. Wow, fascinating. Right,
and תוספות, Tosafot as we mentioned, the first תוספות Tosafot in the
מסכת masechet deals with issues about early שבת and early דאווענינג davening
because where they were, is exactly this: the days were very long
and actually church time was such that Jacob Katz has written an
article about this, about how that impacted how everybody kept time and
the day was structured in a way so that, you know, they
did their nighttime דאווענינג davening while it was still light outside. Yes.
So it could also be that part of what bothers תוספות Tosafot
is the idea of תוספת, tosefet, you're supposed to add. But it
could also be just פלג, Plag, right? No, no, only from פלג
המנחה Plag haMincha on. It's all based on רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
All of these discussions are the end of the day, so you
can say... Now, but if it's a very long day, a שעות
זמניות sha'os zmaniyos hour and a quarter could be two hours. בוודאי.
Bevadai. But yes, it's from פלג, Plag, because it's all רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. And I should say it's possible the other thing that
bothers תוספות in addition to תוספת שבת tosefet Shabbos is somehow it
does deeply disturb us more to be making הבדלה when it's still
שבת, to almost declare a holy day and to say it's no
longer holy and even if in principle I'm not going to do
מלאכה, I'm sort of... there seems to be something much more disturbing
about that, so there's a little bit... there's more resistance, although הלכתית
halachically you are allowed to do that. Yes. Similar issue: once I
דאווען מעריב daven Maariv at פלג, Plag, right at פלג, Plag, and
then went to dinner and had bread, so do I say יעלה
ויבוא? Ya'aleh v'Yavo? It was... I'm not going to get into that.
Do I say רצה והחליצנו? Retzei v'hachalitzanu? All right, I'm sure, but
we're not going to get into that. But I want to understand
normatively, are we saying the only time we can do this is
if there's like a טורח torech or if we just do it
because like, you know, we feel like it? No, תוספות adds the
idea of צורך. tzorech. Okay? Yeah, we פסקן pasken צורך. tzorech. Now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Getting back to the question of
ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos. אמר קידוש אכוס, Amar kiddush akos, which would
seem to imply that it counts. Yeah. Oh yeah, you're יוצא קידוש.
yotzei kiddush. There's another מחלוקת ראשונים, machlokes Rishonim, if קידוש kiddush you're
יוצא, yotzei, there's a מחלוקת ראשונים, machlokes Rishonim, what about other מצוות
mitzvos of שבת or what about if you accepted an early יום
טוב, Yom Tov, are you יוצא מצוות yotzei mitzvos of יום טוב
Yom Tov during the period of תוספת? tosefet? The general assumption is
you're not יוצא מצוות yotzei mitzvos of יום טוב, Yom Tov, I
mean basically it would be like ישיב בסוכה. yashiv b'Sukkah. If you
made an early סוכות, Succos, are you... and you had your כזית
kezayis of bread and whatever and you בנטשט bentched before it got
צאת Tzeis or whatever, are you יוצא? yotzei? The general assumption is
no, there's a discussion in the ראשונים. Rishonim. There is a question
about are you יוצא סעודת שבת yotzei seudas Shabbos when you accept...
you know, of your three סעודות. seudos. And there there's many that
assume yes, that if you're making קידוש kiddush and קידוש kiddush starts
the סעודה seuda and we say you can do an early קידוש,
kiddush, you can do an early סעודה, seuda, but that's discussed. Okay,
let's continue. The גמרא says like this: אמר רב זירא אמר רב
אסי אמר רב אלעזר אמר רב חנינא אמר רב. Amar Rav Zeira
amar Rav Assi amar Rav Elazar amar Rav Chanina amar Rav. Okay,
so a long tradition. בצד עמוד זה התפלל רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי
של שבת בערב שבת. Betzad amud zeh hitpallel Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yosi
shel Shabbos b'Erev Shabbos. Right by this pillar, רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי
Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yosi דאווענד davened שבת when it was still Friday.
כי אתא עולא, Ki ata Ula, when עולא... Ula... came אמר *amar*
no no no you got it all wrong. It wasn't by that
pillar, it was בצד תמרה הוי *betzad timra havai*. It was by
this date palm tree ולא בצד עמוד amod, הוי *velo betzad amud
havai* not by a pillar. ולא רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי הוי *velo
Rebbe Yishmael be'Rebbe Yosei havai* and it wasn't Rebbe Yishmael be'Rebbe Yosei
אלא רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי הוי *ela Rebbe Elazar be'Rebbe Yosei havai*
it was Rebbe Elazar be'Rebbe Yosei. ולא של שבת בערב שבת הוי
*velo shel Shabbat be'erev Shabbat havai* and it wasn't that he דאוונד
*davened* שבת *Shabbat* on ערב שבת *erev Shabbat* אלא של מוצאי שבת
בשבת הוי *ela shel motzaei Shabbat be'Shabbat havai* it was that he
דאוונד *davened* מוצאי שבת *motzaei Shabbat* on שבת *Shabbat*. Of course of
course it highlights maybe they were both true, maybe they were two
different stories. Anyway, but it is fascinating because you know it sort
of gets to the question about the whole מסורה mesorah *mesorah* and
if they really are debating the same case and they got all
the details wrong, it's a fascinating point. Again it's because of what
was said previously in the discussion that whoever וחולק על ישיבתו של
רבו *vecholek al yeshivato shel rabo* I mean we just skipped over
that but that's a very important statement about that you shouldn't only
דאוון *daven* in front of your רבי *Rebbe* or before your רבי
*Rebbe* or show respect you can't actually have a divergent opinion. So
here I think what they're saying is look you have to, I
mean, it's not going to be perfect. So it's a way I
think of softening something that would have been really too hard. Right,
so that's very beautiful and that actually immediately fits in, you know
sort of segues us into the next גמרא *Gemara*. So let's take
a look at the next גמרא *Gemara* because I did mention that
that was a particular רבי אליעזר *Rebbe Eliezer* position, but it's very
nice to sort of read that that's what the גמרא *Gemara* is
sort of getting back to here and it certainly seems to be
an important theme about what we're about to read. So let's keep
on, let's keep on reading. The גמרא *Gemara* says like this: תפילת
הערב אין לה קבע *Tefilat ha'erev ein lah keva*. So this is
the line in the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* that you know there's no
fixed time to the nighttime davening means it can be the entire
night. So the גמרא *Gemara* says מאי אין לה קבע *mai ein
lah keva*? What does אין לה קבע *ein lah keva* mean? אילימא
דאי בעי מצלי כולי ליליא *eileima de'i ba'ei matzli kulei leila* if
it means you can דאוון *daven* the whole night which is what
we assume it means, just say the whole night תפילת הערב כל
הלילה *Tefilat ha'erev kol halaila*. So מאי אין לה קבע *mai ein
lah keva* and it doesn't have a fixed aspect to it? So
כמאן דאמר תפילת ערבית רשות reshut *keman d'amar Tefilat Arvit reshus* because
it's telling you that the nighttime prayer to some degree is only
a רשות reshut. *reshus*, an option not an obligation. Now what exactly
this means is not at all clear because if you remember all
the earlier גמרא *Gemara* says if you miss מעריב *Maariv* you דאוון
*daven* two שחרית *Shacharit*s to make it up. All of them were
assuming that you had to דאוון מעריב *daven Maariv* right in all
these discussions above when we דאוון *daven* you know ערב שבת *erev
Shabbat* you know שבת בערב שבת *Shabbat be'erev Shabbat* and מוצאי שבת
בשבת *motzaei Shabbat be'Shabbat* all of them were discussing does it count
for מעריב *Maariv*. So it could be that all those גמרות *Gemaros*
are assuming תפילת מעריב היא חובה chova? *Tefilat Maariv hi chova* which
is another position which we'll see. Or תוספות *Tosafot* says, תוספות *Tosafot*
says that תפילת ערבית רשות reshut. *Tefilat Arvit reshus* doesn't mean it's
not an obligation. It means it's an obligation it just means that
somehow it like other obligations can override. רשות reshut, *Reshus* compared to
other you know other things. So there's a little bit of a
asterisk like you have to דאוון מעריב *daven Maariv* asterisk if you
have certain other sort of halakhic obligations then you can put this
aside under some cases. That's the way תוספות *Tosafot* reads רשות *reshus*
and sometimes תוספות *Tosafot* makes that point that רשות *reshus* in the
גמרא *Gemara* doesn't mean total רשות *reshus*, it means not as obligatory
as everything else. That's the way תוספות *Tosafot* reads. רמב"ם *Rambam* and
others read that it started as רשות *reshus* but then the practice
was adopted that we all accepted the implicitly as a community the
obligation to do it and then it leaves over a question is
there any relevant aspect now to it having started as a רשות
*reshus* if now we've accepted it as a חובה chova. *chovah*. But
there are, yes, but we're not going to go into it. But
the רשות *reshus* does not mean an absolute רשות *reshus*, it's clear
from the גמרא *Gemara* that it's treating מעריב *Maariv* as an obligation.
Let's see where the גמרא *Gemara* continues with this. Okay, דאמר רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda אמר שמואל *d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel* תפילת ערבית
*Tefilat Arvit* when it comes to the evening prayer, רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel, אומר חובה chova *Rabban Gamliel omer chovah* Rabban Gamliel says it's
an obligation, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua. אומר רשות *Rebbe Yehoshua omer reshus*
Rebbe Yehoshua says it is a רשות *reshus*. אמר אביי *Amar Abaye*
הלכה כדברי האומר חובה *halacha kedivrei ha'omer chovah* we rule like the
one who says it's an obligation. רבא אמר *Rava amar* הלכה כדברי
האומר רשות *halacha kedivrei ha'omer reshus* we rule like it's an option,
again but with the asterisk and with what I just said. Okay,
תנו רבנן Rabbanan. *Tanu Rabbanan* our rabbis taught: מעשה בתלמיד אחד *maaseh
be'talmid echad* there was a story about a certain student שבא לפני
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *she'ba lifnei Rebbe Yehoshua* that came to Rebbe
Yehoshua. אמר ליה Amalei, *Amar lei* תפילת ערבית רשות או חובה Tefillat
Arvit reshut o chova? *Tefilat Arvit reshus o chovah* is it רשות
*reshus* or חובה *chovah*? אמר ליה Amalei, רשות *Amar lei reshus* it's
a רשות *reshus*. בא לפני רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Ba lifnei Rabban
Gamliel* so he was like asking getting another opinion which is not
necessarily problematic because you know that's the whole question once you ask
one פסק *psak* do you go for another פסק *psak*. Maybe there's
an idea of getting a lot of opinions. Anyway so he went
to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel*. אמר ליה Amar lei, *Amar
lei* תפילת ערבית רשות או חובה *Tefilat Arvit reshus o chovah* is
it רשות *reshus* or חובה *chovah*? אמר ליה חובה *Amar lei chovah*
it is an obligation. אמר ליה *Amar lei* so he said to
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel, *Rabban Gamliel* והלא רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua אמר
לי רשות *vehalo Rebbe Yehoshua amar li reshus* but Rebbe Yehoshua told
me it was a רשות *reshus*. So oh big mistake. אמר ליה
*Amar lei* המתן *hamten* wait עד שיכנסו בעלי תריסין לבית המדרש *ad
she'yikansu ba'alei terisin le'veit ha'midrash* until the basically shield bearers until they
come into the בית המדרש Beit Hamedrash, *Beit ha'Midrash*. A very sort
of militaristic image you know like fighting when it comes to תורה
Torah *Torah*, fighting the fight of תורה Torah *Torah*. You will see
that he will be very harsh and very sort of aggressive. So
wait till they wait till they... So wait till the wait till
everybody gets to the בית המדרש. Beit Hamedrash. כשנכנסו בעלי תריסין, kshenichnasu
ba'alei trisin, when the shield-bearers entered, meaning all the תלמידים came into
the בית המדרש, Beit Hamedrash, עמד השואל ושאל. amad hasho'el v'sha'al. So
he said... so he was a plant, he says, ask me when
everybody's in the בית המדרש. Beit Hamedrash. So then he got up
and he asked in publicly, תפילת ערבית רשות או חובה? Is it
a רשות or a חובה? אמר רבן גמליאל חובה. Amar Rabban Gamliel
chova. Now by the way notice that רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel that
you know normally we speak about by a סנהדרין Sanhedrin that you're
פותחין בקטן תחילה, potchin b'katan techila, you want to give everybody an
option to speak. Here he asked everybody who was there and רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel, had to be the first word. And again this
is all going to be, you know, relevant to this story. רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel was the נשיא Nasi I should say, if that
wasn't understood, he was the political head and in the בבלי, Bavli,
through the בבלי Bavli lens, the נשיא Nasi is also the, it's
supposed to play a very important role as the, like, a head
rabbinic authority in terms of being a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. I'll
mention later about a very great, a really excellent article about that.
So here is רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel he's the head of this
בית המדרש, Beis Hamedrash. he's the נשיא, Nasi, he has political power,
he's also the, you know, sort of has a very key rabbinic
role. Okay, so he answers first before anybody has a chance, חובה.
אמר ליה רבן גמליאל לחכמים, Amar leh Rabban Gamliel lachachamim, now that
after he's made his opinion heard, he says to everybody else, כלום
יש אדם שחולק בדבר זה? klum yesh adam shecholek badavar zeh? So
you know, we're going to make this decision by consensus, okay? I
say this, anybody disagree? All right, so anyway, כלום יש אדם שחולק
בדבר זה? klum yesh adam shecholek badavar zeh? Exactly. Anybody disagree? אמר
ליה רבי יהושע לאו, Amar leh Rabbi Yehoshua lav, so Rabbi said
oh no. So אמר ליה, so רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said ולאו
משמך אמרו לי רשות? velo mishmacha amru li reshut? I heard you
say that it was רשות. אמר ליה, so he said to him,
יהושע עמוד על רגליך, Yehoshua amod al raglecha, he doesn't, right, יהושע
Yehoshua stand on your feet, ויעידו בך v'ya'idu bach and let people
testify against you that you said רשות. So you know obviously he's
sort of, you know, just denigrating him in this process, you know,
really asserting his authority. עמד רבי יהושע על רגליו, Amad Rabbi Yehoshua
al raglav, so he stood on his feet. אמר, he said, אלמלא
אני חי והוא מת, ilmalei ani chai v'hu met, if I was
alive and he was dead, יכול החי להכחיש את המת, yachol hachai
lehach-chish et hamet, I could contradict the dead. עכשיו שאני חי והוא
חי, achshav she'ani chai v'hu chai, we're both alive, איך יכול החי
להכחיש את החי? eich yachol hachai lehach-chish et hachai? How could I
contradict the one who is living? Now who is the one that
he said if he were dead I could contradict him? So presumably
the one who's testifying against him and claims that he said רשות,
if he wasn't around I could deny it. I could say that
I'd only said that I said חובה that it's a rumor, it's
false. But one also wonders, you know, since that person hasn't been
mentioned here again, that it's a little bit maybe also referred to
רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel like, you know, if רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
wasn't around here we could have had an open debate about this
issue, but now that he's alive I can't say anything. So he
said it third person. I know, he said exactly. What? He didn't,
it's a little cloaked what he is saying. If he says if
he were dead I could contradict. Who's the he? Is all I'm
asking. I understand that פשט pshat is the person testifying against me,
but it's interesting that that person has not made a reappearance. Okay,
right now the two characters are רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and רבי
יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua But he's not exactly standing up for what, I
know, I'm not saying he is standing up. He's bemoaning the fact
that this is the state of affairs. But is he bemoaning the
fact that he can't deny what he said, or is he bemoaning
the fact that he can't have a debate and actually take a
position because of who רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel, is, he's not allowed
to voice his position. Exactly. An entire culture. Exactly. All right, let's
keep on going, let's keep on going. Okay, so היה רבן גמליאל
יושב ודורש, haya Rabban Gamliel yoshev v'doresh, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel. was
sitting and sort of explicating, giving over the whole, you know, giving
the שיעור. shiur. He was leading the בית המדרש. Beis Hamedrash רבי
יהושע עמד על רגליו. Rabbi Yehoshua amad al raglav. He was like
the guy in the corner with the dunce cap on. He had
to stand on his feet during, everybody else was sitting, he had
to stand on his feet through the whole שיעור. shiur. Okay, עד
שרננו כל העם, ad sherannu kol ha'am, until everybody started sort of
murmuring and, you know, being very upset about the situation. ואמרו לחוצפית
התורגמן, v'amru lehchutzpit hatorgeman, so this חוצפית Chutzpit was the one who
basically, the way it worked is that one person is that the
chief person teaching would say something to, sometimes he was called the
תנא, Tanna, he was called the תורגמן, Torgeman, to another person and
that person would be the loudspeaker. He would be the one that
would sort of say very loudly to everybody or repeat it, maybe
rephrase it. So they said to this guy, basically what they did
is they shut off his mic. Okay, they said לחוצפית התורגמן, lehchutzpit
hatorgeman, עמוד, amod, stop, stop, you know, don't repeat what Rabban... Wait,
he said did he memorize the מסורה or he simply broadcasted? I
always thought that the תנא, Tanna the guy was, was the book.
No, no, so there are, right, right, so there, right, you're right,
there are, I'm sorry, it's called the אמורא, Amora, there are two
roles, I'm sorry, the תנא Tanna is the one that has it
memorized, right, right, the תנא tanna is the one that has memorized
all this stuff, I'm sorry, so it's the אמורא, Amora, we obviously
call the אמוראים Amoraim those that lived after the תנאים, Tannaim, but
the same way a lower-case תנא Tanna. is not רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, but it's the memorizers of the תורה
Torah שבעל פה, a lower-case if you would א אמורא, a amora,
אלף אמורא, aleph amora, is the broadcaster. And here it's referred to
as the תורגמן. Torgeman. So they said לחוצפית התורגמן, lehchutzpit hatorgeman, עמוד,
stop, stop, you know, don't repeat what רבן... Rabban... Gamliel saying anymore.
ועמד *Ve-amad*, he stopped. So basically they turned off רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel*'s mic. Okay, they were fed up with him, they
turned off his mic. Okay, so אמרי Amri, *amri*, what? So they
and there was now אמרי *amri* and they said, what? Yes, yes,
stop. I'm just saying they used the term עמוד *amod* for stopping
as if he had to stand, right, when רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
*Rabbi Yehoshua* had to stand and they told him to stand. Very
good point. So אמרי *amri*, they said, עד כמה נצער וניזיל *ad
kama nitztar ve-neizil*, how long are we going to let רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* sort of afflict us and keep on going?
Like, what type of culture is this? So בראש השנה אשתקד *be-Rosh
Hashana eshtakad*, and in Rosh Hashana last year, צעריה *tzareih*, he afflicted
him. Now this is because רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* and
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua* are always having run-ins because רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua* seems to be clearly the bigger תלמיד
חכם Talmid Chacham, *talmid chacham*, but רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel*
was very concerned about his authority. So there was a famous story
in Rosh Hashana where רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua. *Rabbi Yehoshua* said that
based on the testimony of the new moon couldn't be correct and
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* said it was correct, and רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* had to assert his authority and forced
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua. *Rabbi Yehoshua* to come in front of רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* on רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua. *Rabbi Yehoshua*'s
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, the day רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua*
would have thought was יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. I get to decide,
you come in front of me with your money, with your stick,
you need to violate your יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* to show you
accept my authority. So that's what he bothered us with last year,
okay? בבכורות *Be-bechorot*, and with case of בכורות *bechorot*, במעשה דרבי צדוק
*be-ma'aseh de-Rabbi Tzadok*, דצעריה *de-tzareih*, he afflicted him with the case of
רבי צדוק *Rabbi Tzadok*, another case where רבי צדוק *Rabbi Tzadok* had
a question and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua*, exact same case
like here, you know, and he said עמוד על רגליך וכו' *amod
al raglecha ve-chu'*. Now, by the way, בכורות *Bechorot* and ראש השנה
*Rosh Hashana* might refer to what the cases were about, but they
also might refer to the מסכתות *masechtot* because the Rosh Hashana case
occurs in מסכת maseches, ראש השנה *masechet Rosh Hashana* and the בכורות
*bechorot* case occurs in מסכת Masechet בכורות *masechet Bechorot*. Anyway, he's constant,
but it's interesting, although the one he's been sort of, you know,
right, attacking is רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua, *Rabbi Yehoshua*, they took it
personally because what does that mean about the whole culture of, like,
you know, fear or open and honest debate? הכא נמי צעריה *Hacha
nami tzareih*, here too he's afflicting him. תא ונעבריה *Ta ve-na'avreih*, let's
go and remove him. So let's do a little, what, a palace
coup or whatever. So מאן נוקים ליה *Man nokim leh*, who should
we put up? Why don't we find out? נוקמיה לרבי יהושע *Nokmeih
le-Rabbi Yehoshua*, let's let's put רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua* in
this place. לא, בעל מעשה הוא *Lo, ba'al ma'aseh hu*, he's, you
know, he's like a party to the debate, that would be that
would be too partisan to have רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua*,
right, to have to have רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua, *Rabbi Yehoshua* there.
רש"י *Rashi* says that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel, *Rabban Gamliel* would be
too afflicted by that, it would be too much pain for רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel, *Rabban Gamliel*, but it would seem too partisan anyway.
Let's try to get a third party. So נוקמיה לרבי עקיבא *Nokmeih
le-Rabbi Akiva*, how about רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*? He clearly is like
a huge תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham. *talmid chacham*. לא, דילמא עניש ליה
*Lo, dilma anish leh*, maybe רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel, *Rabban Gamliel* will
punish רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*. Why? דלית ליה זכות אבות *De-leit leh
zechut avot*. Although זכות אבות *zechut avot* sounds to be like metaphysical,
maybe God will punish him, רש"י *Rashi* says very clearly רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel, *Rabban Gamliel*, remember רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel, *Rabban Gamliel* is
the נשיא Nasi *Nasi*, he's descended from the house of the נשיא
Nasi *Nasi*, from the patriarch, from הלל *Hillel*, right, there's, I mean,
you know, the status that comes with birth and therefore he came
from very powerful families. רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* didn't come from powerful
families, so maybe רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* will somehow suffer as a
result of trying to take this position because, you know, רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* still obviously has a lot of power. So
אלא מה *ela mah*? Very well, he married well, that's true, he
married into money, he didn't necessarily marry into, you know, the power
and into, you know, family prestige, right, anyway, okay. So אלא נוקמיה
לרבי אלעזר בן עזריה *Ela nokmeih le-Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah*, let's hear
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya. *Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah*.
דהוא חכם Chacham. *De-hu chacham*, first of all he's wise. דהוא עשיר
*De-hu ashir*, he's wealthy, okay, wealthy is always good in terms of
power, right. והוא עשירי לעזרא *Ve-hu asiri le-Ezra*, he has good יחוס
*yichus*, he can claim family status, he is a descendant, the tenth
descendant of עזרא *Ezra*, who was also a... now עזרא *Ezra* is
an interesting model because עזרא *Ezra* is both עזרא הסופר *Ezra ha-Sofer*
and like the rabbinic type of a model as it were and
he's also the political leader. Okay, so let's get him. What, א
כהן *a Kohen*? So, okay, but that's true, but I don't know
that that's directly relevant to רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben
Azarya, *Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah*. Anyway, okay, דאית ליה זכות אבות *de-it
leh zechut avot*, and he has, you know, the the merit of
the the family, of the fathers. ואי מקיש ליה *Ve-i makish leh*,
did I skip a line? Oh, דאי מקיש ליה *de-i makish leh*,
if he'll be challenged in terms of his תורה Torah. *Torah* knowledge,
מפרק ליה *mefarek leh*, he'll be able to answer it. דהוא עשיר
*De-hu ashir*, he's wealthy, דאי אית ליה לפלוחי לבי קיסר *de-i it
leh le-puluchei le-vei keisar*, אף הוא אזל ופלח *af hu azal ve-palach*.
If he has to go do some service in the house of
the Caesar, he can also do it because the patriarch actually had
a lot of, you know, business in the house of the Caesar
and it actually required him to have his own wealth in order
to pay bribes and other things, right, and there's also just give,
right, sort of I think, you know, tribute, exactly. Anyway, והוא עשירי
לעזרא *ve-hu asiri le-Ezra*, he's the tenth of Ezra, דאית ליה זכות
אבות *de-it leh zechut avot*, ולא מצי עניש ליה *ve-lo matzi anish
leh*, and he has this the the parentage and he cannot and
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* won't be able to take it
out on him. I should mention again this is an article, I'll
tell you more about it in a minute, by Dvora Steinmetz, it's
a great article, I'll let... it's actually available on PDF, I'll put
it up on the web, I'll send it out. It's... It's called
like, 'Must the Patriarch Know עוקצין?', which is about the difference between
the בבלי Bavli and ירושלמי Yerushalmi's takes. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi understood, which
was closer to the facts, that the נשיא Nasi, was not always
the biggest תלמיד talmid חכם, I mean not talking about רבי יהודה
הנשיא, Rebbi Yehuda HaNasi, but you know that that family wasn't always
and did not have to see him through the lens of a
תלמיד talmid חכם. So it was okay to see him through the
lens of a political leader, whereas the בבלי Bavli very much sees
him through that lens. So it's very interesting that first the first
thing they mention about his qualifications is you know that he's a
חכם. You know, the whole political aspect sort of are a little
bit secondary. Anyway and here taking place in the בית המדרש. Beis
Hamedrash. There's a parallel story in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and it doesn't
take place in the בית המדרש Beis Hamedrash. but in a בית
הועד. Beis Hava'ad. In the sort of house of gathering, in a
public, you know, in a public gathering. So like a בית כנסת
Beis Knesses or like right some type of maybe you know exactly.
It's not the same sort of you know scholarly setting. Anyway let's
keep on going. So so let's get רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rabbi
Elazar ben Azarya. אתו ואמרי ליה, Atu va'amrei lei, they came and
they said to רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya ניחא
ליה למר דהוי ריש מתיבתא? Nicha lei lemar dehavei Reish Mesivta? Would
you like to be the ראש ישיבה? Rosh Yeshiva? Not just ריש
מתיבתא, Reish Mesivta, I mean it's about the נשיא Nasi. but they're
calling it ריש מתיבתא, Reish Mesivta, okay? Would you like to be
the ראש ישיבה? Rosh Yeshiva? אמר להו, Amar lehu, איזיל ואימליך באנשי
ביתא, eizeil ve'imlich be'inshei beisa, you know what, let me ask my
wife. אזל ואימליך בדביתהו, Azal ve'imlich bedevittai, he went and he asked
his wife. אמרה ליה, Amrah lei, she said to him, דף כ"ח
עמוד א', Daf Kaf-Ches Amud Aleph, סופם מעבירין לך, sofam ma'avirin lach,
you know what, I wouldn't get involved at this stage, you know,
things will settle down and then they're going to depose you. So
it'll be very temporary. Right, exactly. אמר לה, Amar lah, he says
back to her, לישתמש איניש יומא חד בכסא דמוקרא ולמחר ליתבר, lishamesh
inei yoma chad bekassa demokre ulemachar lispari, a person should use just
for one day a beautiful glass chalice even if it breaks the
next day. So what, it'll be just for a little bit of
time, so that was a common saying apparently. At least it'll be
you know חשוב chashuv for the time that it will be. אמרה
ליה, Amrah lei, she said to him, if you don't want my
advice why did you ask? אמרה ליה, Amrah lei, she said to
him, לית לך חיוורתא, leis lach chivvusa, you don't have white hair,
so you won't be respected. ההוא יומא בר תמני סרי שני הוה,
Hahu yoma bar tamsrei shne hava, this is the famous story, he
was 18 years old, this רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rabbi Elazar ben
Azaryah איתרחיש ליה ניסא, Isracheish lei nissa, a miracle occurred, ואהדרו ליה
תמני סרי דרי חיורתא, Vehadru lei tamsrei darei chivvusa, and it's interesting
ואהדרו ליה, vehadru lei, returned to him, it didn't reverse. But anyway,
he got 18 rows of white hair. היינו דקאמר רבי אלעזר בן
עזריה, Hainu deka'amar Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya, הרי אני כבן שבעים שנה,
harei ani keven shiv'im shana, the משנה Mishna. we quoted before, I
am like 70 years old, ולא בן שבעים שנה, velo ben shiv'im
shana, I'm not really 70 years old because I look I turned
to look that old. תנא. Tanna. So he's very young by the
way, right? He was 18 years old. I mean a kid and
they were going to make him the ראש ישיבה. Rosh Yeshiva. Right.
No no no they were quoting a משנה. Mishna. הרי אני כבן
שבעים שנה harei ani keven shiv'im shana was a משנה. Mishna. אגדתא
Aggada quotes the משנה. mishnah Okay תנא. Tanna, Okay תנא, Tanna, what?
Did they do this so that they could control him? Let's take
a look. Okay תנא, tanna, אותו היום סלקוהו לשומר הפתח, Oso hayom
silkuha leshomeir hapetach, that day that רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar
ben Azaryah took the place, they removed the guard on the door.
There was a guard guarding the door of the בית המדרש. Beis
Hamedrash. וניתנה להם רשות לתלמידים ליכנס, Venitna lahem reshus letalmidim likaneis, and
they said open it's open school anybody can come in. It used
to be very selective who can come in. He opened up he
threw wide open the door. Open admission. Thank you, that's what I
was looking for. רבן גמליאל מכריז ואומר, DeRabban Gamliel machriz ve'omeir, רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel used to be announcing and saying, כל תלמיד שאין
תוכו כברבור אל יכנס לבית המדרש, kol talmid she'ein tocho kevaro lo
yikaneis leveit hamedrash, any student that the inside is not like the
outside. He was very exclusive. So it wasn't only about his own
power. I mean to a degree it's also about power, I want
to control everything and therefore anybody who I don't know the inside's
like the outside is totally you know no like doesn't appear to
be something he isn't, but is as sincere as they appear to
be. Only somebody I know is 100% good. If not that way
אל יכנס לבית המדרש, lo yikaneis leveit hamedrash, can't come into the
בית המדרש. Beis Hamedrash. But that day they threw open the doors
wide. ההוא יומא אתוספו כמה ספסלי, Hahu yoma itoseifu kamma safsalei, that
day many like rows of chairs were added to the בית המדרש.
אמר רבי יוחנן פליגי בה אבא יוסף בן דוסאי ורבנן, Amar Rabbi
Yochanan paligi bah Abba Yosef ben Dosai verabbanan, so there's a debate
of אבא יוסף Abba Yosef and רבנן. חד אמר אתוספו ארבע מאה
ספסלי, Chad amar itoseifu arba me'ah safsalei, 400 chairs were added or
rows of chairs, 400 excuse me, 400. וחד אמר שבע מאה ספסלי,
Vechad amar sheva me'ah safsalei, 700. Okay a little exaggerated. But anyway
the point is the point is they really increased their admissions. Okay
tons of people now join the בית המדרש. הוה קא חלשה דעתיה
דרבן גמליאל, Hava kachalsha daateih deRabban Gamliel, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel? now
felt very you know what's the word? Not weakened, dispirited. Right. אמר
דלמא חס ושלום מנעתי תורה מישראל, Amar dilma chas veshalom maniyati Torah
miYisrael, maybe my policy God forbid led to Torah being you know
held back from Israel. אחזו ליה בחלמיה, Achazu lei bechelmeih, they showed
him in a vision, תצפי חוורי דמליאן קטמא, Tatzpei chivrei demalyan kitma,
exactly what he had always thought. Which is, this is רבן גמליאל,
Rabban Gamliel. he sees. Ah the heavenly retinue. Okay he had a
dream and he saw white casks filled with ashes. They look white
on the outside but on the inside they're black and they're ashes.
Exactly what he was suspected why he wanted to do his policy.
To have a number of... Exactly. Or the sincerity also. But one
minute. The גמרא says ולא היא. v'lo hi. Although that's what he
saw in a dream, it's not really the truth. ההיא ליתובי דעתיה
הוא דאחזו ליה. Hahi leyituvai da'atiah hu de'achzu lei. They did it
to make him feel better but the reality was, yeah, he did
have a very bad policy in place and it's very clear which
one the גמרא sides with. All right, תנא, Tanna, so now, okay,
now, one question though, what do you think it means that he
thinks that, well you know, I'm going to read a little bit
more and then we'll go back to that. תנא, עדיות בו ביום
נשנית. Eduyos bo bayom nishneis. The whole מסכת עדיות maseches Eduyos was
taught on that day. Okay, and there's a couple places where the
משנה mishnah says בו ביום, בו ביום, bo bayom, bo bayom, which
means that day where they, which is the day that רבי אלעזר
בן עזריה Rebbi Elazar ben Azaryah? was made the ראש ישיבה rosh
yeshiva and they opened up the doors and they taught and they
learned and they taught מסכת, no they taught, they constructed מסכת עדיות
maseches Eduyos because what's עדיות? Eduyos? עדיות Eduyos is getting testimony from
not only the exclusive rabbinic elite. You want all the facts on
the table. You want to hear anybody that might have heard some
testimony relevant to, you know, bring in any facts that we can
find because we want to really find the truth of תורה. Torah,
So, the open door policy allowed them to have מסכת עדיות maseches
Eduyos and you'll remember before, we ruled like רב יהודה Yehuda because
he was in מסכת עדיות maseches Eduyos and that's called בבחירותא. bechirusa.
That's called the choice teachings is what we know from מסכת עדיות,
maseches Eduyos, which only was possible because he opened the door. Okay,
now, back to רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel What he did was on
that day, wow, well, yeah, one minute, right. Take, so now it
says, one minute, one minute, okay, בו ביום נשנית bo bayom nishneis
וכל היכא דאמרינן בו ביום, vechol heicha de'amrinan bo bayom, whenever any
משנה mishnah says "on that day this is what was taught," ההוא
יומא הוה. hahu yoma hava. It was the day that עדיות Eduyos
was started, the day that רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rebbi Elazar ben
Azaryah. was made the ראש ישיבה. rosh yeshiva. ולא הייתה הלכה שהייתה
תלויה בבית המדרש שלא פירשוה. V'lo haysa halacha shehaysa teluya beveis hamidrash
shelo perushuha. And here again, it emphasizes the value of the open
admissions. There was no הלכה that was in doubt that was not
somehow clarified. You have so many people there, so many different voices,
and now you are able to actually, you know, clarify any question,
anything that is in question. So two points here, basically everything I'm
sharing with you about this is based on that article by Devorah
Steinmetz, I'll send it to you. But two points here, number one
is clearly this is in, well not clearly, but anyway what it
is doing is once you realize it, it's clear, in contrast to
the whole, you know, it's not just the number of students, it's
the very difference of what happens when you silence opposition, you know,
and you don't allow for there to be discussion, and you open
up the, and you have as many possible voices as possible. Not
just one voice, but hundreds of voices. And that's the type of
a culture and that actually allows for things to be resolved. And
it's not by putting down, silencing the other voices. The other thing
is that, that when רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said, "Maybe I held
back תורה Torah from ישראל," Yisrael who is he holding, what does
it mean? Does it mean he's holding it back from the students
that came into the בית מדרש? beis midrash? Or maybe it's even
more profound than that. He's actually holding back תורה Torah, itself, because
תורה Torah, is suffering by only having such an exclusive policy. Only
allowing the few people in the בית מדרש, beis midrash, silencing anybody
that disagrees with you. So maybe his whole policy actually impacted תורה.
Like you were saying, all of עדיות Eduyos was taught only when
this new policy was in place. I think that's a very important
point because what it means is unlike popular opinion which suggests that
diversity confuses, diversity of opinion is necessary to gain clarity. Exactly, right,
it sharpens everybody's opinion and another interesting model with, not to push
it too much, I use is like the whole thing about, you
know, Britannica and Wikipedia. When Wikipedia started, everybody thought it was a
joke, right? Obviously you get experts and you pay them and you
get them to write Encyclopedia Britannica, you know, online or whatever, and
they're obviously going to be the authoritative encyclopedia. And of course Wikipedia,
you know, because people correct one another and so on and it's
not always correct, but you know there's a, it's not done by
experts and look at still what it produced. Okay, so now the
גמרא continues. ואף רבן גמליאל לא מנע עצמו מבית המדרש. V'af Rabban
Gamliel lo mana atzmo mibeis hamidrash. Even רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel had
such a love of תורה, he's not going to come out as
a total bad guy, right, because it's not all about his power.
He had such a love of תורה that even when he was
deposed, he did not keep himself out of the בית מדרש. beis
midrash. אפילו שעה אחת, Afilu sha'ah achas, even for one hour. דתניא,
Detanya, we taught in a משנה mishnah in ידיים, Yadayim, בו ביום,
bo bayom, and remember בו ביום bo bayom means on this day,
בא יהודה גר עמוני לפניהם בבית המדרש. ba Yehuda ger Amoni lifneihem
beveis hamidrash. יהודה a convert, an עמוני Amoni convert came in front
of them, the rabbis, in the בית מדרש. beis midrash. אמר להם,
Amar lahem, מה אני לבוא בקהל? mah ani lavo bakahal? Can I
be, enter into the community? Can I, you know, marry a Jewish
woman? Because אמר ליה רבן גמליאל, amar lei Rabban Gamliel, so רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said, אסור אתה לבוא בקהל, asur ata lavo bakahal,
you can't. Not surprising, again takes an exclusive, you know, approach, only
certain people are allowed in. אמר ליה רבי יהושע, Amar lei Rabbi
Yehoshua, רבי יהושע said, מותר אתה לבוא בקהל, mutar ata lavo bakahal,
you can come in. Very consistent. Now, אמר ליה רבן גמליאל, amar
lei Rabban Gamliel, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said, והלא כבר נאמר valo
kvar neemar לא יבוא עמוני ומואבי בקהל ה'. lo yavo Amoni u'Moavi
bikhal Hashem. That an עמוני Amoni and a מואבי, Moavi, it's a
פסוק. pasuk. אמר ליה רבי יהושע, Amar lei Rabbi Yehoshua, רבי יהושע
said, וכי עמון ומואב במקומן הן יושבין? vechi Amon u'Moav bimkoman hein
yoshvin? What, you think that עמון Amon and מואב, Moav, they're not
the people who now identify as עמון Amon and מואב Moav are
not the original עמון Amon and מואב. Moav. כבר עלה סנחריב. Kvar
ala Sancheiriv. סנחריב מלך אשור Sancheriv melech Ashur ובלבל את כל האומים.
u-bilbel et kol ha-umim. סנחריב Sancheriv came and he confused all the
nations, he deposed people and transferred, you know, transferred people from their
land and people that now including other people who identify as עמון
Amon and מואב, Moav, like what we call now the Egyptians are
nowhere near the Egyptians of the תורה, right? I mean, you know,
there, you know, even the Egyptians of Cleopatra, Cleopatra wasn't the Egyptians
that we read in the תורה, right? So anyway, so דכל דפריש
מרובא פריש, de-chol de-parish me-ruba parish, anybody who separates separates from the
majority. So basically we can assume that even if somebody is did
I skip a line? Oh, I skipped a line. No I didn't.
ובלבל את כל האומים שנאמר על ידי ישעיה. u-bilbel et kol ha-umim
she-neemar al yedei Yeshaya. ואסיר גבולות עמים ועתודותיהם שושתי, v'asir gevulot amim
v'atudoteihem shoseti, I have I have removed the boundaries of nations and
I've plundered their treasures, ואוריד כביר יושבים, v'orid kabir yoshvim, and I've
brought down with force their inhabitants. So this is סנחריב Sancheriv talking
basically, I've transferred all the people. דכל דפריש מרובא פריש, de-chol de-parish
me-ruba parish, anybody now, we have to assume they come from the
majority of people, the majority of people are not עמון Amon or
מואב Moav or עמלק Amalek or any problematic people. So we don't
have any of these problems anymore. אמר ליה רבן גמליאל, Amalei Rabban
Gamliel, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said, ולא כבר נאמר, v'lo kvar neemar,
what do you mean? The פסוק pasuk says, ואחרי כן אשיב שבות
בני עמון נאום ה׳, v'acharei chen ashiv shevut benei Amon neum Hashem,
וכבר שבו, v'kvar shavu, I will return the, you know, the returning
of the people of עמון, Amon, and the people of עמון Amon
presumably he knew were, you know, were in their place now. So
one nation has been restored. אמר ליה רבי יהושע, Amalei Rabbi Yehoshua,
ולא כבר נאמר v'lo kvar neemar another פסוק pasuk says, ושבתי את
שבות עמי ישראל, v'shavti et shevut ami Yisrael, ועדיין לא שבו. v'adayin
lo shavu. No, because you know when the nations will be restored
will be when the people of ישראל will be restored. That hasn't
happened yet, so we do not have to worry about the identity
of people. מיד התירו לבוא בקהל, Miyad hitiro lavo bikhal, so they
allowed him to come into the community. Now you will notice of
course, right the difference of, you know, not the obvious echo of
keep out, stay, you know, come in, stay out, רבי יהושע come
in, they opened it up, they let him come in. But there's
another big difference here which is sort of in רבי יהושע was
the דסי dasi here. No, no, besides that, no they're assuming he
was. I mean I don't know they're assuming this was the day
that he was the ראש ישיבה. Rosh Yeshiva. No, but the difference
is it doesn't contradict. Exactly. רבן גמליאל says one thing, רבי יהושע
says another, and the next line is רבן גמליאל opens והלא כבר
נאמר, v'halo kvar neemar, right? Why was that the echoes of והלא
כבר אמרו לי משמך, v'halo kvar amru li mishmecha, right? That we
said before. How dare you, you know, how dare you contradict me.
Now they're entering into an honest debate. Right? So now רבן גמליאל,
he's not only staying there, he's accepting the culture that רבי יהושע
has put into place. I mean he doesn't have the power now
to silence רבי יהושע. But at least here's a very powerful counter,
you know, sort of to what we saw earlier, that now he
actually is having this type of an honest debate. Okay. Now the
גמרא says, okay, אמר רבן גמליאל, Amar Rabban Gamliel, so said רבן
גמליאל, הואיל והכי הוא, hoil v'hachi hu, oh, since this is the
way things are looking, okay, looks like you know I'm deposed, אזיל
ופייסיה לרבי יהושע, azil u-fayseia l'Rabbi Yehoshua, let me go and make
up with רבי יהושע. כי מטא לביתיה, Ki mata l'veiteh, when he
came to his house, חזינהו לאשיתא דביתיה דמשחרן. chazinhu l'ashita d'veiteh d'mshachran.
He saw the walls of his house were black, of רבי יהושע.
אמר ליה, מכותלי ביתך אתה ניכר שפחמי אתה, mikotlei beitcha ata nikar
she-pachami ata, from the walls of your house it's clear that you
are a metal what's it called? a blacksmith, a blacksmith. Right? Yeah,
רש״י Rashi also says maybe he works with coal but probably a
blacksmith. אמר ליה, so he said back to him, אוי לו לדור
שאתה פרנסו, oy lo l'dor she-ata parnaso, woe to the generation that
you are its, like leader, you are the one that... רבי יהושע
said back to רבן גמליאל, שאי אתה יודע בצערן של תלמידי חכמים,
she-i ata yodeia b'tzaran shel talmidei chachamim, you don't know about the
about the pain of the תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. Remember before the
תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim were being pained by רבן גמליאל, they were
צרי, tzarei, here you don't know the צער, tzaar, how just our
situation, you know, the pain we suffer, במה הם מתפרנסים ובמה הם
ניזונים, bameh hem mitparnesim u-vameh hem nizonim, how we have to make
a living and how we have to feed ourselves. You know, you're
rich, you're נשיא, you think, you know, you're removed from all of
this. You don't really understand the common person and you don't understand
even your fellow scholars. אמר לו, Amar lo, נעניתי לך, naaniti lach,
I submit to you. מחול לי, mechol li, forgive me. לא אשגח
ביה, Lo ashgach beih, he didn't pay attention to him, he didn't
want to. So then he says עשה בשביל כבוד אבא, aseh bishvil
kvod aba, do it for the honor of my father, פייס. pyes.
So then he was then he accepted it. So presumably he held
his father in more regard, which is interesting because the whole thing
about כבוד אבות kvod avot before. Anyway, that somehow tipped the scales.
רבן גמליאל׳ס Rabban Gamliel's father is one of the ten martyrs. Okay,
so maybe that's it. אמר, so he said, מאן ניזיל ולימא להו
לרבנן, man neizil v'lima lehu l'rabanan, who's now going to tell the
Rabbis that we've changed our that you forgave me and maybe I
can get back my position? Wait a minute. אמר להו ההוא כובס,
Amar lehu hahu koves, so a certain launderer said to them, אנא
אזילנא, ana azilna, I'll go. שלח להו רבי יהושע לבי מדרשא, Shlach
lehu Rabbi Yehoshua l'vei midrasha, so רבי יהושע sent to the בית
מדרש Beis Medrash the following message, מאן דלביש מדא יילבש מדא. man
d'lavish mada yilbash mada. The person who wears the cloak, like, you
know, the cloak of authority, should continue to wear the cloak of
authority. מאן דלא לביש מדא, Man d'la lavish mada, the person who
doesn't, has never had that, you know, never worn the cloak before,
יימר ליה למאן דלביש מדא שרי מדך ואנא אלבשיה, yeimar leh l'man
d'lavish mada shari madach v'ana elbashieh, should he say to the one
who wears the cloak: you take off your cloak and I'll wear
it? This he's always had that, he's always had this position. So
אמרו רבי עקיבא לרבנן, Amru Rebbi Akiva leRabbanan, Rabbi Akiva said to
the Rabbis, טרוקו גלי, Truku galei, ולו ליתו עבדי דרבן גמליאל ולצערו
לרבנן. vlo leisu avdei deRabban Gamliel uletzaru leRabbanan. Again, afflicting the Rabbis.
He said, lock the doors before we open the doors, lock the
doors. Who are we going to keep out? To keep out רבן
גמליאל, to keep out his servants because he didn't realize that רבי
יהושע, how do you know that this is what רבי יהושע is
saying? Maybe it's רבן גמליאל who's trying to force his way back.
So רבי עקיבא said, lock the doors, don't let the servants of
רבן גמליאל come into the בית מדרש Beit Midrash and oppress us,
afflict us. We want to keep רבן גמליאל out. טרוקו גלי Truku
galei means lock the doors? Yes. Okay. So, okay, so again, the
interesting parallel to the opening of the doors and to the צער.
tza'ar. אמר רבי יהושע, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua, so that didn't work. So
רבי יהושע said, מוטב דאיקום ואזיל אנא לגביה. Mutav de'eikum ve'ezil ana
legabei. I think I better go personally and let them know that
we made up. אתא טרף אבבא, Asa taraf abava, he came and
knocked on the door. אמר ליה, and he said, מזה בן מזה
יזה. Maze ben maze yaze. Similar type of analogy: the sprinkler, the
son of the sprinkler, like the ashes of the פרה אדומה Parah
Adumah should sprinkle. ושאינו לא מזה ולא בן מזה, Veshe'eino lo maze
velo ben maze, somebody who's never sprinkled, never been the son of
the sprinkler, יאמר למזה בן מזה, Yomar lemaze ben maze, should say
to the sprinkler, the son of the sprinkler, מימך מי מערה ואפרך
אפר מקלה. Meimecha mei me'arah ve'afrecha eifer mikleh. Your waters are cave
waters and your ashes are like ashes from roasting. So, how's it
right for somebody who's never had that position of authority to depose
רבן גמליאל? So the גמרא says, אמר ליה רבי עקיבא לרבי יהושע,
Amar lei Rabbi Akiva leRabbi Yehoshua, נתפייסת? nitpayasta? רבי יהושע, have you
been appeased? כלום עשינו אלא בשביל כבודך. Kelum asinu ela bishvil kevodecha.
We only did it for your honor. למחר אני ואתה נשכים לפתחו.
Lemachar ani ve'ata nashkim lepitcho. Tomorrow you and I will go to
the door of רבן גמליאל. This is a way they had in
Rome, in Roman society, that the patron, you would come to the
door of your patron in the morning to show and give him
honor and so on. So to show, it's a way of showing
this is the person who is over you, who's your authority, who
you rely on. So anyway, we will go to his door tomorrow
to show that we accept him, we accept his authority. אמרי, so
now they said, היכי נעביד? Heichi na'avid? Wait a minute, what are
we going to do now with רבי אלעזר בן עזריה? Rebbi Elazar
ben Azaryah Let's not forget about him. נעבריה, Na'avrei, should we remove
him from his post? גמירי מעלין בקודש ואין מורידין. Gimiri ma'alin bakodesh
ve'ein moridin. You raise somebody, you don't lower them. Now we can't
depose רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rebbi Elazar ben Azaryah נדרוש מר חדא
שבתא ומר חדא שבתא. Nidrosh mar chada shabta umar chada shabta. Should
they take turns alternating one week and the other? אתי לקנאויי, Asi
lekinu'ei, then there'll be a jealousy because each one is going to
think they're the boss. אלא לידרוש רבן גמליאל תלתא שבתא ורבי אלעזר
בן עזריה חדא שבתא. Ela lidrosh Rabban Gamliel tlata shabta veRebbi Elazar
ben Azaryah chada shabta. רבן גמליאל would do three weeks and רבי
אלעזר בן עזריה Rebbi Elazar ben Azaryah one week. So it'll be
clear who's the boss, but רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rebbi Elazar ben
Azaryah will still have his role of authority one week out of
every four. והיינו דאמר מר, Ve'hainu de'amar mar, that's when we teach,
שבת של מי הייתה? Shabbat shel mi haytah? When there was a
discussion in another place they say "whose week was it?", meaning who
was the authority, who was the head of the בית מדרש Beit
Midrash that week? רבי אלעזר בן עזריה הווה. Rebbi Elazar ben Azaryah
hava. So there you see that now we've instituted a rotation that
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rebbi Elazar ben Azaryah at least was one
week out of four. ואגב באותה תלמיד רבי שמעון בן יוחאי הוה.
Ve'agav be'ota talmid Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai hava. If you're wondering who
the student was it started off as, was רבי שמעון בר יוחאי.
Rebbi Shimon bar Yochai. Now, I just want to make two or
three comments to end this. First of all, we don't even appreciate
how beautifully constructed this is in addition to all the themes. If
you look at Jeffrey Rubenstein's article you'll see that it has a
perfect chiastic structure. Everything that sort of started building up and then
was parallel coming down. And you see it by the end, you
have the תלמיד at the beginning and the תלמיד at the end
and it's a whole chiastic structure, the whole thing. The other important
point to note is that by having this, first of all, the
fact that רבי אלעזר בן עזריה's Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya wife was
right. The important thing to note is that they institutionalized this new
type of a culture because now רבן גמליאל is not the only
voice. Now you're actually institutionalizing multiple voices and this rotation and this
sort of, so in the end a change did occur. It wasn't
like we went all back to the old ways. And the final
really profound insight that he has is the whole theme here ongoing
about inside and outside. Not only who's in the בית מדרש Beit
Midrash and out of the בית מדרש, Beit Midrash, but רבן גמליאל's
תוכו כברו, tocho kevaro, does the inside look like the outside? And
that is, and
so that at the beginning of it there was an issue about
you look too young, and the black hair which become white. And
then in
the end he looked at the house and he said it was
black and he said you're just a normal blacksmith. So רבן גמליאל
is being misled by the externals. He sees the externals as, רבי
אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya looks too young and now
he looks like a blacksmith and all those types of things. And
the idea is that you want to make sure people are sincere
on the inside, but what it leads you to do is pay
too much attention to the, you yourself are misled by the externals.
And how do you really know what's going on on the inside?
So that is also a very sort of theme that plays out
throughout this is inside and outside. Okay, I will upload the sources
later. We're on דף כ״ח עמוד א׳. Daf Kaf Chet Amud Alef.
It's the bottom, toward the bottom of דף כ״ח עמוד א׳. Daf
Kaf Chet Amud Alef. We just had the change of leadership, that
we had רבן גמליאל was ousted and רבי אלעזר בן עזריה was
made the new ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva or the new נשיא. We
saw the change. First of all, we added many benches, hundreds of
benches according to different opinions. And then we have the following, which
is that on that day even the things that were being left
pending were decided, the דברים שהיו תלויין ועומדין devarim she-hayu tluyin v'omdin
were decided on that day. So that is what we're looking at
right now. And even עדויות, Eduyot, מסכת עדויות, Masechet Eduyot, which is
testimony, which we generally assume that that whole מסכת was formed on
that day. It says בו ביום נשנית מסכת עדיות, bo bayom nishnet
Masechet Eduyot, on that day the tractate of testimony was taught. And
then it says וכל היכא דאמרינן בו ביום, v'chol heicha d'amrinan bo
bayom, wherever we say on that day, ההוא יומא הוה, hahu yoma
hava, it's that day. Whenever we have a משנה that says בו
ביום, bo bayom, it means on this day that רבי אלעזר בן
עזריה was appointed as head of the ישיבה. So, ולא היתה הלכה
שהיתה תלויה בבית המדרש שלא פירשוה, v'lo hayta halacha she-hayta tluya b'veit
hamidrash she-lo peirshuha, there was no law that was pending in the
house of study that they didn't explain on that day. So it
was a very productive day. ואף רבן גמליאל לא מנע עצמו מבית
המדרש, v'af Rabban Gamliel lo mana atzmo mi-beit hamidrash, and even רבן
גמליאל didn't hold himself back from the house of study, even though
he was no longer the head of it. That shows he was
not full of pride. And now we turn to the second line
on דף כ״ח עמוד ב׳, Daf Kaf Chet Amud Bet, and here
we have an interesting case. It says תנן התם, tenan hatam, we
learned there, in another place we learned elsewhere, we learned about עמון
ומואב מה הן בשביעית, Ammon u-Moav ma hen b'shvi'it, the nations of
עמון Ammon and מואב, Moav, which were neighboring Israel, what's their status
in the sabbatical year? Is the land considered part of the land
of Israel for the purposes of the sabbatical year or is it
considered outside of the land of Israel? Now the background here is
that there are many different דאורייתא, De-Oraita, biblical, and דרבנן, De-Rabbanan, rabbinic
laws regarding the land of Israel. And in the sabbatical year, שביעית,
Shvi'it, you're not supposed to work the land. However, there's another concept
which is the giving of מעשר, ma'aser, tithes. And there were different
tithes given in different years. And in the sabbatical year, there's no
tithe because the land is left fallow and whatever grows is ownerless,
it's הפקר. hefker. So but what about outside of Israel? Outside of
Israel, there's no שביעית, Shvi'it, however there is the concept of מעשר.
ma'aser. And in some years you give מעשר עני, ma'aser ani, the
tithe for the poor, and in some years you give מעשר שני,
ma'aser sheni, the second tithe, which you eat in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Now
the question here was what do you do in these lands of
עמון Ammon and מואב? Moav? Are they like Israel or not like
Israel? And it's decided that they are going to give מעשר עני,
ma'aser ani, the poor man's tithe, in the seventh year. Why? Because
in Israel there is no food available because nobody's planting, and so
the poor people would have nothing to eat. So the rabbis decided
that in עמון Ammon and מואב Moav they should treat it like
a regular year and give מעשר עני ma'aser ani so the poor
people would have what to eat. Okay, so that's the background for
this discussion that's going on.